Hey guys, welcome back to our IELTS Listening course.
Let's take a look at these questions.
What are they asking us to do?
As you can see, they require details involving
numbers, such as dates, prices, and quantities, or
spelling, like phone numbers, names, and postal codes.
Many of you think that these are easy.
However, we are here today to make sure
that you will never lose any points for
this type of question.
Today's lesson is divided into two parts.
First, we will learn about how to listen
for numbers on their own.
And second, we will learn about how to
handle combinations of numbers and letters.
Without further ado, let's begin.
Normally, you will be asked to listen to
numbers in two main types of questions.
First, completion tasks, like form completion in part 1,
table or flowchart completion in part 2,
and summary completion in part 4.
Second, multiple choice questions with one correct answer
in part 2, and some other rare cases
in other parts of the listening test.
So what is your task here?
It is very simple.
Listen to the recording and find the answers,
which here are in the number form, such as 150 or 4:30 pm.
Then the main challenge for this question type
is simply how to listen to numbers correctly.
So let's get to how to deal with this.
For listening to numbers alone,
there are two main scenarios.
The easier scenario involves quantities or prices,
where the answer is shorter.
The harder scenario involves times and dates.
To handle these scenarios perfectly,
there are four things you need to understand
and master how to write them in your answer sheet to
prevent losing points in easy questions.
1. Punctuation
2. Currency
3. Dates
4. Time
1. Punctuation
In English, when separating thousands,
you can use a comma or you don't have to
write down any punctuation with the number at all.
However, you should not put a full stop
or an apostrophe here.
For example, one thousand is written as this
or this, not this.
However, for decimal numbers, we use a full
stop or a period.
Four and a half or 4.5 is written as this.
Never write this.
Just remember, comma for thousands, dot for decimals.
2. Currency
Usually, you will hear dollars or pounds.
Normally, the question will provide the symbol, so
you must not write the currency symbol again.
In rare cases, if the question does not
provide the symbol, please remember that the symbol
always goes before the number.
And just like before, use a full stop
for the cents.
3. Dates
This can be confusing because the format
changes depending on the country.
In the UK, they use day, month, year,
like 18th May.
In the US, they use month, day, year,
like May 18th.
The good news is that for IELTS, both formats are acceptable.
However, remember to follow the word
and number limits from the instructions.
For instance, the 18th of May is counted
as three words and one number.
But 18th May or 18 May is just
one word and one number.
Also, when writing dates,
you should always capitalize the month.
Write April with a big A, never a small a.
4. Time
You can use either a colon or
a full stop to separate hours and minutes.
7:00 can be 7.00
or 7 o'clock.
Also, if the recording mentions a.m or p.m like this,
you must not include a.m
because it is already mentioned in the question.
Finally, we should not forget our friend, distractors.
First, the recording might provide a wrong answer
or an unselected option first,
then the correct one after.
In this case, all you need is to listen closely.
Second, the recording might provide a seemingly right answer,
but then the speaker corrects it by themselves.
This one is a bit trickier.
For example, one could say, My phone number
is 01234990 and then correct it by saying,
My mistake, the last two numbers are 09,
not 90.
Here, you need to correct the number by yourself.
Now, let's move to the second part.
Listening to numbers and letters.
Number combinations like postal codes, license plates, emails,
and room or house numbers often mix digits and letters.
The golden rule here is accuracy.
Do not add hyphens or spaces
unless you clearly hear them.
If you have mastered listening to numbers only,
this part is not challenging at all.
However, please be cautious of letters that sound
very similar to numbers or to other letters.
Watch out for these pairs.
8, H and A
E and I, B and P
T and D, G and J
M and N
S and X
Also, be careful with numbers that sound alike,
specifically the "-teen" versus the "-ty", such as
15 versus 50.
But don't worry, we have already prepared many
listening practice questions for you after this lesson
to help you master these distinctions.
That's it for today's lesson.
Don't forget to do the exercises and practice
what you've learned regularly.
Goodbye and see you in the next lesson.